it's only about you say something about
contentment with the basic requisites
with the basic requisites
there's something that most people would
like to have
if they thought about it
to be satisfied
with that which is available readily
that which is available readily
available to you actually
you know good enough food
good enough clothing good enough shelter
and enough medicine
but that's even though we have those
things available
there's no contentment because there is
no um
because people are careless
in regard to their desires
contentment requires maintenance
requires maintenance
it requires you to to
[Music] to foresee to foresee
things
before they arise to foresee a
possibility for proliferation before it
arises so it's just
so it's just
obviously as everything else that you
somebody's just starting it's going to
be unpleasant because of the discomfort
and it's going to
it's gonna require some doing and
learning but uh once a person develops that habit
but uh once a person develops that habit
then yeah they don't need to be
constantly uh obsessing over the simplicity and and
uh obsessing over the simplicity and and
keeping things simple and requisites
because they will become the way they
prefer to live
but until until they reach that point
you you do need to keep yourself in
check that's pretty much it
that's pretty much it
just ask yourself well hold on do i need
this much or do i need this many
so can i
is this sufficient
and most often the answer is yes
absolutely and the reason why people always go for
and the reason why people always go for
more is because
of the
unquestioned attitude
attitude
towards avoiding discomfort
people don't want this comfort
it's like do i need a mattress of that
thickness well no really
but you know if i don't if i don't have
it um
sufficiently comfortable i won't sleep
at night well you might not sleep first
night or second night when third night
you'll be so tired you'll sleep on a
concrete block
so
you train yourself in that regard
obviously you don't have to
you don't have to do it sort of without
that purpose as in just just try to
renounce everything and
and then not eat and sleep on a stone
i mean you know if that brings the
unwholesome states to decrease and
wholesome states increase yeah by all
means but doing it in itself because sometimes
but doing it in itself because sometimes
people can get intoxicated with that
sort of the tanga determination
which is misguided
like you're just doing it out of some
sort of matchup you know
thing to prove like yeah you know i
don't lay down when i sleep and so on
why what's the relationship between that and
what's the relationship between that and
unwholesome states decreasing and
wholesome states increasing usually ends
up increasing the conceit and so on
so you always want to keep it practical
that's how you know you won't be able to
kind of wear off too far
into into conceited determination of i'm
the best i'm the toughest
keep it practical like things that are
genuinely practical
things that are not necessary
that can then support
your practice towards wakefulness and
towards diminishing of the unwholesome
states
so yeah the little things you have to
throw everything away but yeah ask
yourself is my mattress too soft
could i sleep on the harder surface
what would what would the result be
will be less sleep because you wouldn't
be able to overly enjoy because it's not
too comfortable
which means okay so that could bring the
unwholesome state to the crease and hold
some stakes to increase
means i won't be indulging in the sleep
so you remove your mattress and sleep on
a wooden board
but if you're doing it out of some sort
of
self-advertisement as well
i mean it can still arrive it can still
be made wholesome
so in a way it's still it's still okay
but uh it's important to distinguish the
two whether it's done out of just some sort
whether it's done out of just some sort
of inspirational determination or if
it's done for the purpose of practically
supporting your practice yeah becoming
stronger being able to yeah tougher you
can take more than means you'll be
bothered less because you can take more
yeah you can take physical pain and take
more by taking less yeah exactly
but yeah if you if your body is
dependent on a certain amount of comfort
uh well you would struggle
if you were to leave
the the softness of your home
the softness of your home
your environment your bedroom you would
struggle you so ask yourself like is is
my current situation really making me
um
tougher and able to endure the elements
as the buddha said that you should
because you know some of the paints have
to be abandoned by enduring
so like
you can ask yourself honestly then well
would i be abandoning any of those
things if i can't even give up my
five inch mattress
yet you're supposed to be enduring cold
and heated
mosquitoes and insects discomfort
or just an evening meal
eating eating less people sure eating
less exactly yeah
is it necessary would like will i die if
i don't eat until tomorrow will this
hunger kill me am i genuinely like
fainting and i don't know
losing losing my senses no
no so it's just a bit of discomfort
it's also in terms of shelter
you know
trying to
get your surroundings
in terms of your shelter
perfectly spiritual anyway so that you
can practice yeah yeah become a stronger
person well no that's that's what that's all
well no that's that's what that's all
the rules in that there's a certain
misguided inspiration and determination
it's just it's more like it's more on
the level of people's identity than what
they do and what they're practicing
it's not really
rooted properly
uh
on the level of actually trying to
uproot the identity
belongings appropriation sense of self
life and existence
and existence
you know people have a little shrine and
they have a little setup
i mean again we have to differentiate
we're talking about a like a casual
lay person who's practicing or you're
talking about somebody who's really sort
of going for it
committing to it full on
if you're just doing it part-time that's
fine these little reminders
these little reminders
can be helpful because
well yeah you're not you're not giving
up the life
uh but if you're actually a monk or
something like that then
yeah it's not really
i mean the monk who's practicing
or towards
because shrines are can be focuses of
your intention to practice well
intention to practice well
really i mean again as i said if you
live a busy lay life and you have no
intention of leaving it then yeah a
little shrine can remind you of certain
values in the same sense the buddha said yeah
in the same sense the buddha said yeah
like if you're not doing anything else
go and visit the place with the target
that was born and so on because it will
make you think about him as in think
about the values of enlightenment
but having shrine and worship shrine for the
having shrine and worship shrine for the
sake of your practice
well it's just completely redundant it
makes no difference literally
it's neither
contributing well it could be taking
away if you think that's what practice
is
but i think most people don't think that
they might do another habit of some sort
of like pleasing identity
my shrine
my my arjun my this my that
which is fine
but uh if you want to arrive at any
any relevant distinction that needs to
be overcome